welcome to Chocolate series episode 5. a
friend of the channels
in the US he makes chocolate bars and
asked a question that might have been
earlier this year or even last year
um how does 100 chocolate work in ice
cream and that is what we're gonna look
at today this is a very old Italian 100
chocolate or cocoa Mass gelato it's
solid as a rock it's just come out of
freezer so I'm gonna film all the other
bits and hopefully it's defrosted by the
time we get around to it
thank you
[Music]
so 100 chocolate
this is the one I've used
um Willy's Cacao is based in Devon in
England he did a really interesting TV
series years ago I lived in Devon at the
time and went down to see him but he was
Bloody closed would you believe it so
they produced chocolate for use in
cooking not just sweet foods but
obviously 100 chocolate can be used in
Savory Foods as well as the
cow boosts the flavors of other things
in your recipes
and they liked to talk about that on
that program I'll try and find a link
somewhere and put something or maybe
into the website
it's really good quality stuff but it's
not often used now because it's really
bitter if you if you eat it like it is
it's not designed to be eaten like this
you wouldn't pick up a hundred percent
bar of chocolate or cacao and just bite
into it it would taste horrible
but when you look online there are there
is some evidence that confident
chocolate was used in various recipes
now had a look at this one here which
was a classic Italian cocoa Mass gelato
so I thought it'd be quite interesting
to make this one as part of the
chocolate series and see how it turns
out it's still just you know softening
up here it's been out for a couple of
minutes now it's gonna need probably at
least another five minutes to stop it
and soften to soften up enough so let's
talk about how we make this gelato
[Music]
so what I started to do and forgot to
film it was to chop up the entire block
of this hundred percent cacao it's 180
grams worth
then what you start with is again your
milk as always in a pan and you slowly
heat that up whilst adding in your
sugars to completely dissolve them then
you're going to add in all of your 100
chocolate or cocoa mass and then get it
completely melted in that base and
looking really nice and silky smooth
like this
get it to about 65 to 70 degrees
Centigrade when you're going to take it
off the heat and then put it in a
blender or a food processor and at this
stage you're going to Blitz it for 30
seconds to a minute to make sure that
the ingredients are completely
emulsified
once that's done take it out of your
machine and put it in a container to
completely chill down in the fridge
[Music]
once it's completely chilled down if
there's any solid residual left on the
top of your covering take that off you
don't want to lose those and then one
final stir before it goes in your
machine churn away again as normal this
took about 10 to 12 minutes and my
machine might take longer might take
less for you once it's ready you're
going to load up your tub and put it in
a freezer
foreign
[Music]
how hard is this stuff still
solid so we're just gonna leave it there
for a few minutes more and we're back uh
a couple of minutes more actually that's
all it took to be fair wasn't a huge
amount of time something to remember
about gelato is it served a warmer
temperature than ice cream so this is
kind of expected especially of a
classical Italian recipe let's get some
scooped up and see what it turned out
like
foreign
[Music]
there we go scooped quite nicely it's
got a really nice rich color it's kind
of color wise in between a chocolate
sorbet and chocolate American style ice
cream
so just to confirm with those that might
be interested in my gold my eyes
can't read that
yeah ingredients
cow
that's it
cacao spelled with a k
let's see
anyway nothing else added no sugars no
milk powders no nothing
milk chocolate is generally milk powders
added to the chocolate as it's being
produced rather than milk liquid because
that would make it seize
um
quite interested to see what this tastes
like so let's Dive In
foreign
just pause it there so we could uh talk
about the ice cream it's really
surprising it surprised us both
it's got a great texture there's this
recipe has not been adjusted at all this
is an exact copy of the recipe that I
found online the link is below this is
what the website looks like so we've
made their ice cream here
something to note is
if you think you're gonna get something
really horrible and bitter
you're wrong
it's really smooth it's
it lingers
which some gelato doesn't because it's
lower fat but this does and I think it's
probably because you're making it with
this chocolate it it's still there
lingers on the back of your tongue and
you can still taste it now
so that's really nice it's a nice smooth
chocolate flavor it's not bitter at all
actually is it
no so it's a
smooth kind of chocolate
basically me personally I'd probably
replace a little bit of the sugar with
dextrose just to soften it up if you
wanted to eat it straight from the tub
but if not then just make this recipe
exactly as it is I would say choose a
really good quality
100 cacao don't just buy any old crap
without knowing and doing your research
find one that is meant to be really
really good has some reviews because I
think this is important this is what
you're tasting here you're tasting the
pure cocoa Mass
just another term that a lot of people
use cocoa Mass chocolate is often cocoa
mass that has sugar and or milk added to
it so that's when it becomes chocolate
before that point when you're just
dealing with the cacao it's actually
kakamas that your your using
so yeah this has really surprised me I'm
I'm shocked at how good this is I'm
shocked that it's not bitter and I'm
really impressed with the texture and
and overall this recipe is excellent so
I do recommend this one to those who
want to have a go at something different
in the world of chocolate ice cream so
hope you enjoyed this unique take on a
luxury chocolate ice cream don't forget
to like And subscribe hit us up on Kofi
as well I'll put the link below and
we'll see you next time
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]